Guide to the Michael Peterson papers, 1961-2019 and undated, bulk 1972 RL.01020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Michael Peterson papers
1961-2019 and undated, bulk 1972
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Peterson, Michael (Michael I.)
RL.01020
3 Linear Feet
Novelist, veteran of the Marine Corps in Vietnam, and alumnus of Duke University. Convicted in 2003 of murdering his wife Kathleen Peterson; a retrial was ordered in 2011. In 2017 Peterson submitted an Alford plea to the reduced charge of manslaughter, was sentenced to time already served, and was set free. Chiefly consists of correspondence and writings that pertain to three novels written by Michael Peterson: A Time of War, The Immortal Dragon, and The Enemy. Peterson served in the Marine Corps and based these novels around his experiences during the Vietnamese conflict. The writings contain handwritten and typed drafts of the three novels. While an undergraduate at Duke University, Peterson served as editor of the student newspaper, The Duke Chronicle. Issues of this newspaper printed during his editorship are bound together and included within the collection.
500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Michael Peterson papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1990 and 2019.
Collection Overview
Collection chiefly consists of correspondence and writings that pertain to three novels written by Michael Peterson: A Time of War, The Immortal Dragon, and The Enemy. Peterson served in the Marine Corps and based these novels around his experiences during the Vietnamese conflict. The writings contain handwritten and typed drafts of the three novels. While an undergraduate at Duke University, Peterson served as editor of the student newspaper, The Duke Chronicle. Issues of this newspaper printed during his editorship are bound together and included within the collection.
Novelists, American -- 20th century; Duke University -- Periodicals; Peterson, Michael (Michael I.); Vietnam War, 1961-1975
- Michael Peterson papers, 1961-2019, bulk 1972, 4 boxes
  - Correspondence: Zuckerman, Albert, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Various publishers and replies, 1972-1989 (Box 1)
  - Audio script of A Time of War, undated (Box 1)
  - Descriptions of The Enemy, undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscript draft of The Enemy, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings, undated, 3 of 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings, undated, 8 of 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Setting copy of The Immortal Dragon, 1983, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Typescript of A Time of War, 1983, 4 of 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Typescript of A Time of War, 1983, 7 of 11 folders (Box 3)
  - Clippings, newspapers and magazine articles about The Immortal Dragon and A Time of War, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1961-2001 and undated (Box 3)
  - Behind the Staircase, 2019 (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Autobiographical book written by Peterson. Gift of Eric Smith.
  - Clippings, newspapers and magazine articles about The Immortal Dragon and A Time of War, 1988-1990 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - The Duke Chronicle, 1964-1965 (Oversize-folder 1)